Hi.
This is John Stewart and this how to set up your ground tarp or your footprint for setting up your tent.
Most tents now days come with a footprint or a ground cloth.
These help for protecting the bottom of the tent from moisture, sharp objects, stumps, roots and other things.
Most footprints come fitted to the bottom of the tent so that there's no overhang on the outside of the tent when you set the tent on top of it.
These are real nice because you don't have to do any folding of the ground cloth or anything like that.
Ground cloths can be tarps, tyvec, plastic sheeting, anything like that, that you can put on the ground to be a base layer to protect the bottom of your tent from moisture and other objects.
These things need to trimmed to the size of the bottom of your tent so that the water doesn't catch if it rains and flow up under your tent and pull up.
If the water pulls up underneath your tent.
it can saturate through and come into your tent in the middle of the night.
So, with your ground cloths you always want to make sure you have them trimmed to the size of the bottom of your tent to where your tent sits right over the top of it.
This is how to set up a ground cloth or footprint for setting a tent.